<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Gaia Sky</title>
    <link>https://gaiasky.space/</link>
    <description>Recent news on Gaia Sky</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
      <atom:link href="https://gaiasky.space/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" /> 
      <item>
        <title>Gaia Sky 3.6.10</title>
        <link>https://gaiasky.space/news/2025/gaiasky_3.6.10/</link>
        <pubDate>Mon, 21 Jul 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid>https://gaiasky.space/news/2025/gaiasky_3.6.10/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Just before the summer holidays, we are happy to announce the release of &lt;strong&gt;Gaia Sky 3.6.10&lt;/strong&gt;. This is a release that improves on 3.6.9 by bringing a handful of minor improvements and quality-of-life updates, and a lot of bug fixes. Additionally, it enables new versions of the &lt;a href=&#34;https://gaiasky.space/resources/datasets#default-data&#34;&gt;base data&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href=&#34;https://gaiasky.space/reosurces/datasets#hi-res-textures&#34;&gt;high resolution textures&lt;/a&gt; packs, and a new &lt;a href=&#34;https://gaiasky.space/resources/datasets/#vt-earth-diffuse-sentinel&#34;&gt;virtual texture dataset based on Sentinel-2 data&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Here is a screenshot with that Sentinel-2 dataset, which goes down to a resolution of 10 meters/pixel:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;figure class=&#34;fig-center fig-post&#34;&gt;&lt;picture&gt;&#xA;      &lt;source srcset=&#34;https://gaiasky.space/img/2025/07/svt-sentinel-barcelona.jxl&#34; type=&#34;image/jxl&#34; /&gt;&#xA;      &#xA;      &lt;source srcset=&#34;https://gaiasky.space/img/2025/07/svt-sentinel-barcelona.avif&#34; type=&#34;image/avif&#34; /&gt;&#xA;      &lt;img src=&#34;https://gaiasky.space/img/2025/07/svt-sentinel-barcelona.jpg&#34; width=&#34;70%&#34; style=&#34;width:70%;&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;decoding=&#34;async&#34; /&gt;&#xA;    &lt;/picture&gt;&lt;figcaption style=&#34;margin: 0 auto; width:70%;&#34;&gt;&#xA;            &lt;h4&gt;The Sentinel-2 virtual texture in Gaia Sky.&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;        &lt;/figcaption&gt;&#xA;&lt;/figure&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;You can get this dataset in Gaia Sky 3.6.10. The dataset key is &lt;code&gt;vt-earth-diffuse-sentinel&lt;/code&gt;. See a  video in BlueSky &lt;a href=&#34;https://bsky.app/profile/did:plc:lyzlck7lyaeo5g5xcu3raydh/post/3ltowaie5z22l&#34;&gt;showcasing the virtual texture sentinel dataset&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;features&#34;&gt;Features&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Localize Wikipedia API queries for object information.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Add file-level cache to TLE subsystem. TLE files are also cached per-group to avoid unnecessary sequential calls to fetch the same file. By default, the TTL for TLE files is 1 hour.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Directory structure of virtual texture tiles now accepts more formats (&lt;code&gt;levelx&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;levelxx&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;x&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;xx&lt;/code&gt;).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Set default virtual texture cache size to 10. Add information tooltip to cache size in preferences window.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Add markers for towns and landmarks. Night lights go out with ambient light in PBR shader.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Country perimeter lines disappear when the camera gets close to the surface of the Planet.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Add new attributes to dataset definition format: &lt;code&gt;links&lt;/code&gt; (now accepts multiple sources as links), &lt;code&gt;creator&lt;/code&gt; (the creator or curator of the dataset), &lt;code&gt;credits&lt;/code&gt; (specific attribute for credits instead of adding them to the description; multiple strings accepted).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Add translation of object names to French.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;bug-fixes&#34;&gt;Bug Fixes&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Typo in default shader class (&lt;code&gt;u_emissionCubemap&lt;/code&gt; -&amp;gt; &lt;code&gt;u_emissiveCubemap&lt;/code&gt;) prevented emissive/night cubemaps from working.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Add &lt;code&gt;nightCubemap&lt;/code&gt; as alias to &lt;code&gt;emissiveCubemap&lt;/code&gt; in material component.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Add &lt;code&gt;specularValue&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;specularValues&lt;/code&gt; as aliases to &lt;code&gt;specular&lt;/code&gt; in material component, with floating point number parameters.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Properly filter directories when building the SVT quadtree structure to avoid incorrect &amp;lsquo;Wrong directory name format&amp;rsquo; warnings.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Deactivating atmospheres causes night texture to apply uniformly to all planet as if it were a regular emissive texture.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Procedural generation window does not fit in the window with the new UI theme. Fix layout by introducing scroll panes and resizing elements.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Layout issue in right pane of dataset manager window prevented it from using scroll, causing the window to be too large in some cases.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Layout issue and tooltip text in datasets component.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Move &lt;code&gt;genVersionFile&lt;/code&gt; task to the top of the dependency list (before &lt;code&gt;compileJava&lt;/code&gt;) so that we always have the correct file available.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Mend wording in new data pack notification window.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Typo: Korou -&amp;gt; Kourou; Remove titles in object names I18n files.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;</description>
      </item> 
      <item>
        <title>Gaia Sky 3.6.9</title>
        <link>https://gaiasky.space/news/2025/gaiasky_3.6.9/</link>
        <pubDate>Wed, 02 Jul 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid>https://gaiasky.space/news/2025/gaiasky_3.6.9/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Edit (2025-07-03):&lt;/strong&gt; Update post with fixes in patch release &lt;strong&gt;3.6.9-2&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Exactly one month after Gaia Sky 3.6.8, today we are proud to release &lt;strong&gt;Gaia Sky 3.6.9&lt;/strong&gt;. This new version brings some exciting features, like &lt;strong&gt;motion trails&lt;/strong&gt; for star and particle groups, a new &lt;strong&gt;Turkish translation&lt;/strong&gt;, and a new &lt;strong&gt;API (v2)&lt;/strong&gt;, and fixes some bugs. Keep reading for the full list of changes included in this release.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;figure class=&#34;fig-center fig-post&#34;&gt;&lt;picture&gt;&#xA;      &lt;source srcset=&#34;https://gaiasky.space/img/2025/07/motion-trails.jxl&#34; type=&#34;image/jxl&#34; /&gt;&#xA;      &#xA;      &lt;source srcset=&#34;https://gaiasky.space/img/2025/07/motion-trails.avif&#34; type=&#34;image/avif&#34; /&gt;&#xA;      &lt;img src=&#34;https://gaiasky.space/img/2025/07/motion-trails.jpg&#34; width=&#34;70%&#34; style=&#34;width:70%;&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;decoding=&#34;async&#34; /&gt;&#xA;    &lt;/picture&gt;&lt;figcaption style=&#34;margin: 0 auto; width:70%;&#34;&gt;&#xA;            &lt;h4&gt;Motion trails in Gaia Sky 3.6.9.&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;        &lt;/figcaption&gt;&#xA;&lt;/figure&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;new-features--improvements&#34;&gt;New Features &amp;amp; Improvements&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Add motion trail effect, which stretches stars and particles in the velocity direction. Can be toggled off in the settings.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Add Turkish translation, contributed by Erdem Uygun.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Migrate go-to-object operation in the camera info pane to use the smooth transitions API, which creates seamless, bumpy-free rides between two camera states.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Add a new API v2, which re-names and re-organizes the single access port we had in the previous API into several modules grouped by function. It also improves documentation and standardizes function and parameter names when possible.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Adapt REST server and console to also accept APIv2 calls.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Add new setting to enable and disable notification messages, and add checkbox to preferences window. Notifications are off by default. Fixes &lt;a href=&#34;https://codeberg.org/gaiasky/gaiasky/issues/847&#34;&gt;#847&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Update monospace fonts to include all supported characters, now using Liberation Mono.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Add missing characters to font files to ready them for the Turkish translation.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Left and right trigger buttons (LT, RT) in gamepads to control slider values in gamepad GUI.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Update default lens flare shader.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Add &lt;code&gt;generateIndex&lt;/code&gt; attribute to particle sets, so that the index can be omitted for sets that do not need it (which is most of them).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;bug-fixes&#34;&gt;Bug Fixes&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Fix issues with upper- and lower-case conversions not using the correct locale.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Star glow effect flickers due to using a different method to render the billboard depending on whether the effect is active or not.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Big bug fix campaign in scripting. All scripting tests were reviewed and fixed so that they all run fine.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Add missing &lt;code&gt;&amp;quot;&lt;/code&gt; character to fonts, fix custom and messages interfaces&amp;rsquo; computation of position coordinates.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Dataset highlight API call not working properly.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Use concurrent set as collections in event manager to avoid concurrent modification exceptions.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Proper motions produce index out of bounds due to incorrect computation of maximum number of arrows.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Correct many instances where the wrong locale is used to convert strings to upper and/or lower case. Enable star name localization for the index and labels.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Properly scale camera mouse scroll and drag operations with the current frame rate.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Disable OpenAL system.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Use &lt;code&gt;RGBA16F&lt;/code&gt; float format for the lens flare ping-pong buffer, otherwise AMD APUs show banding artifacts. Fixes &lt;a href=&#34;https://codeberg.org/gaiasky/gaiasky/issues/846&#34;&gt;#846&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Resolve redirects for Wikipedia titles, as the API does not resolve redirects automatically. This leads to 403 errors.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Make sure &lt;code&gt;versionFile&lt;/code&gt; task is executed when packing the app by setting the right dependencies.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Adjust layout and width of about window to avoid UI overflow.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;performance-improvements&#34;&gt;Performance Improvements&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Use &lt;code&gt;GL_RGB16F&lt;/code&gt; instead of &lt;code&gt;GL_RGBA16F&lt;/code&gt; format (omitting the alpha channel) for internal post-processing effects buffers (lens flare, bloom, etc.). This saves some VRAM, especially useful in integrated graphics.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Set a default value of 0.4 scale for the lens flare effect to minimize fill rate and make the ping-pong pass much faster.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;code-refactoring&#34;&gt;Code Refactoring&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Harmonize and consolidate star and particle set creation methods under the same class.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;build-system&#34;&gt;Build System&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Disable OptFlowCam export option for keyframes in Flatpak in order to avoid Python dependencies.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Upgrade to Gradle 8.14.2, which supports Java 24.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Update to bundled JRE 24 in packages.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;documentation&#34;&gt;Documentation&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Add new APIv2 package-level documentation.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;</description>
      </item> 
      <item>
        <title>Gaia Sky 3.6.8</title>
        <link>https://gaiasky.space/news/2025/gaiasky_3.6.8/</link>
        <pubDate>Mon, 02 Jun 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid>https://gaiasky.space/news/2025/gaiasky_3.6.8/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Today we release &lt;strong&gt;Gaia Sky 3.6.8&lt;/strong&gt;. It brings a major UI refresh, significant performance improvements, and many new features and bug fixes. Keep reading to know more.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;figure class=&#34;fig-center fig-post&#34;&gt;&lt;picture&gt;&#xA;      &lt;source srcset=&#34;https://gaiasky.space/img/2025/05/3.6.8-release.jxl&#34; type=&#34;image/jxl&#34; /&gt;&#xA;      &#xA;      &lt;source srcset=&#34;https://gaiasky.space/img/2025/05/3.6.8-release.avif&#34; type=&#34;image/avif&#34; /&gt;&#xA;      &lt;img src=&#34;https://gaiasky.space/img/2025/05/3.6.8-release.jpg&#34; width=&#34;70%&#34; style=&#34;width:70%;&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;decoding=&#34;async&#34; /&gt;&#xA;    &lt;/picture&gt;&lt;figcaption style=&#34;margin: 0 auto; width:70%;&#34;&gt;&#xA;            &lt;h4&gt;The new welcome window in Gaia Sky 3.6.8.&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;        &lt;/figcaption&gt;&#xA;&lt;/figure&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;new-features--improvements&#34;&gt;New Features &amp;amp; Improvements&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;user-interface&#34;&gt;User Interface&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Major UI overhaul: consolidated fonts, updated themes, removed deprecated components.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Improved visual quality: increased padding and higher image resolution in UI.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Switched to Inter as the default label font.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Panels in the main UI now expand when the mouse hovers over the buttons.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Welcome window enhancements:&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Displays the list of enabled datasets.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;New &lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;Recommended Datasets&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt; option for one-click download and launch.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Updated background image.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;usability-enhancements&#34;&gt;Usability Enhancements&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Time and calendar:&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Julian date tab added to date/time dialog.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Time zone support improved; system-default time zone now used.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Dialogs remember the last opened tab (e.g. Preferences, About).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;New star texture selector added to Preferences.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;New object debug tool available via the debug panel—inspect and edit component fields.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Pointer coordinates display disabled by default (can be re-enabled in Preferences).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Console output:&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Messages and full log can now be copied to the clipboard.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Bookmark improvements:&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Bookmarks can now include camera position, orientation, time, and settings.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Bookmark information dialog added (accessible via right-click).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Empty folder bookmarks are removed automatically.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Bookmark operations persist immediately.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Invalid characters are now restricted in bookmark and folder names.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;See &lt;a href=&#34;https://gaiasky.space/news/2025/new-bookmarks&#34;&gt;this blog post&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;api--scripting&#34;&gt;API &amp;amp; Scripting&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Added:&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;setCameraDirectionEquatorial()&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;setCameraDirectionGalactic()&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Enhanced &lt;code&gt;goToObjectSmooth()&lt;/code&gt; with solid angle and sync options&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Stars and particles now support a new shading style: &lt;code&gt;default&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;twinkle&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Added Thiele-Innes conversion script and support in the Gaia NSS processor.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;hr&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;bug-fixes&#34;&gt;Bug Fixes&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Fixed incorrect formatting of uptime duration.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Julian vs Gregorian calendar automatically selected based on date.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Fixed layout issues in Preferences and other dialogs.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;UI components:&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Image button alignment corrected.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Anchoring of the top info interface improved to prevent jitter.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;First UI text size adjusted.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Fixed crash when setting data directory to a root drive in Windows (&lt;a href=&#34;https://codeberg.org/gaiasky/gaiasky/issues/825&#34;&gt;#825&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Fixed crash due to early resolution of &lt;code&gt;attitudeindicator.png&lt;/code&gt; path when changing data directory (&lt;a href=&#34;https://codeberg.org/gaiasky/gaiasky/issues/795&#34;&gt;#795&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Improved orbit rendering:&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Constant true anomaly spacing used for high-eccentricity orbits.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Better handling of edge cases in Keplerian-to-Cartesian conversion.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Reused GZipped file streams no longer break on non-gzipped JSON files.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Context menu in bookmarks pane now positioned correctly.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Error window layout made consistent.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Visibility dialog now properly handles &amp;lsquo;Invisible&amp;rsquo; object types.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;hr&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;performance-improvements&#34;&gt;Performance Improvements&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Replaced &lt;code&gt;Apfloat&lt;/code&gt; with &lt;code&gt;Quadruple&lt;/code&gt;: faster 128-bit floating point math with adequate precision. See &lt;a href=&#34;https://tonisagrista.com/blog/2025/quadruple-joins-party/&#34;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://tonisagrista.com/blog/2025/quadruple-joins-party/&#34;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; for some performance benchmarks.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Reduced short-lived object allocations in many systems.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Major speed-up in label rendering via task refactoring.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Star size factors now cached instead of recalculated per frame.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Internal maps replaced with faster, boxing-free versions.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Half-precision (16-bit) floats now used for non-critical star/particle magnitudes.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Particle updates split over multiple frames to reduce frame drops.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Old particle and variable record types unified into a compact, immutable &lt;code&gt;Particle&lt;/code&gt; record.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;PointCloudData&lt;/code&gt; reimplemented using records with a more compact memory footprint.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://gaiasky.space/news/2025/performance-improvements&#34;&gt;This blog post&lt;/a&gt; covers some of these performance improvements in more detail.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;hr&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;code-refactoring&#34;&gt;Code Refactoring&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Removed duplicate star/particle index arrays.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Replaced boxed integers with primitives.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Top-K particle sorting now uses a priority queue.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;All shader files renamed to use the &lt;code&gt;.glsl&lt;/code&gt; extension.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;hr&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;build-system&#34;&gt;Build System&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Upgraded to libGDX 1.13.5.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Default builds now use JRE 24 with Generational ZGC for lower latency.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Java source compatibility updated from 17 to 20.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Gradle upgraded to 8.13.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Install4j AUR package URL updated to &lt;code&gt;gaiasky.space&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Added test infrastructure:&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Includes tests for Keplerian-to-Cartesian conversions.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Enabled JUnit dependencies.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;gdx-tools&lt;/code&gt; moved to compile-only dependency.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Enabled logging for Gradle test runs.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;hr&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;documentation&#34;&gt;Documentation&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Improved descriptions for many fields in the attribute map JSON file.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;hr&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;merge-requests&#34;&gt;Merge Requests&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Merged &lt;code&gt;quadruple&lt;/code&gt; branch (128-bit math support).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Merged &lt;code&gt;particle-update-refactor&lt;/code&gt; branch (particle update system overhaul).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;</description>
      </item> 
      <item>
        <title>New Catalog: Gaia DR3 Best</title>
        <link>https://gaiasky.space/news/2025/new-catalog-dr3-best/</link>
        <pubDate>Mon, 02 Jun 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid>https://gaiasky.space/news/2025/new-catalog-dr3-best/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Today we make available a brand new catalog in &lt;strong&gt;Gaia Sky&lt;/strong&gt;, derived from the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cosmos.esa.int/web/gaia/dr3&#34;&gt;Gaia Data Release 3 (DR3)&lt;/a&gt; dataset. This catalog is a &lt;strong&gt;handpicked collection of the most precise stellar measurements&lt;/strong&gt; available in DR3, designed for applications where &lt;strong&gt;accuracy in parallax and astrometric fidelity&lt;/strong&gt; is essential. This catalog includes a total of 646,400 stars, with a clear bias toward brighter magnitudes. It is a small, non-LOD (non-Level-of-Detail) catalog, designed for broad compatibility. It will be the recommended star dataset starting from Gaia Sky 3.6.8.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;It is ideal for:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Laptops&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;VR&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Low-end desktops&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Devices without dedicated GPUs in general&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Use cases where performance and simplicity matter more than completeness&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;br&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;figure class=&#34;fig-center fig-post&#34;&gt;&lt;picture&gt;&#xA;      &lt;source srcset=&#34;https://gaiasky.space/img/2025/05/dr3-best-hammer.jxl&#34; type=&#34;image/jxl&#34; /&gt;&#xA;      &#xA;      &lt;source srcset=&#34;https://gaiasky.space/img/2025/05/dr3-best-hammer.avif&#34; type=&#34;image/avif&#34; /&gt;&#xA;      &lt;img src=&#34;https://gaiasky.space/img/2025/05/dr3-best-hammer.jpg&#34; width=&#34;70%&#34; style=&#34;width:70%;&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;decoding=&#34;async&#34; /&gt;&#xA;    &lt;/picture&gt;&lt;figcaption style=&#34;margin: 0 auto; width:70%;&#34;&gt;&#xA;            &lt;h4&gt;Hammer projection of the new Gaia DR3 Best catalog.&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;        &lt;/figcaption&gt;&#xA;&lt;/figure&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-does-it-include&#34;&gt;What does it include?&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;Gaia DR3 Best&lt;/em&gt; catalog includes:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;646,400 stars&lt;/strong&gt;, carefully selected from the 1.8+ billion in Gaia DR3.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;All stars with &lt;strong&gt;relative parallax error ≤ 0.4%&lt;/strong&gt; for bright stars (&lt;code&gt;gMag&lt;/code&gt; &amp;lt; 13.1).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;All stars with &lt;strong&gt;relative parallax error ≤ 0.002%&lt;/strong&gt; for faint stars (&lt;code&gt;gMag&lt;/code&gt; &amp;gt;= 13.1).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;The full set of &lt;strong&gt;Hipparcos&lt;/strong&gt; stars, cross-matched and merged into the dataset.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This makes it ideal for high-precision visualization, distance estimation, nearby star studies, or any work requiring only the cleanest subset of the Gaia DR3 catalog.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-another-gaia-catalog&#34;&gt;Why another Gaia catalog?&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Gaia DR3 is a treasure trove, but not all stars are created equal when it comes to measurement quality. This dataset is &lt;strong&gt;suitable for low-end devices&lt;/strong&gt;, and distills the &lt;strong&gt;most trustworthy data&lt;/strong&gt; from the full release, eliminating sources with:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Negative or low-quality parallaxes&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Non-finite magnitudes&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Poor astrometric solutions&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s a breakdown of how we got from 1.8 billion stars to 646k:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;table&gt;&#xA;  &lt;thead&gt;&#xA;      &lt;tr&gt;&#xA;          &lt;th&gt;Step&lt;/th&gt;&#xA;          &lt;th&gt;Count&lt;/th&gt;&#xA;      &lt;/tr&gt;&#xA;  &lt;/thead&gt;&#xA;  &lt;tbody&gt;&#xA;      &lt;tr&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;Initial Gaia DR3 entries&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;1,811,709,771&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;      &lt;/tr&gt;&#xA;      &lt;tr&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;Rejected due to parallax (criteria + negatives)&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;1,805,626,704&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;      &lt;/tr&gt;&#xA;      &lt;tr&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;Rejected due to non-finite magnitude&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;5,455,190&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;      &lt;/tr&gt;&#xA;      &lt;tr&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;Final stars selected&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;&lt;strong&gt;646,400&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;      &lt;/tr&gt;&#xA;  &lt;/tbody&gt;&#xA;&lt;/table&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This dataset loads fast, uses less memory, and is &lt;em&gt;visually cleaner&lt;/em&gt; in 3D than the full Gaia DR3 catalog.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;magnitude-distribution&#34;&gt;Magnitude distribution&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The stars span a wide range of magnitudes, with the majority in the range &lt;strong&gt;8 to 12&lt;/strong&gt;. Here&amp;rsquo;s the magnitude histogram:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;figure class=&#34;fig-center fig-post&#34;&gt;&lt;picture&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://gaiasky.space/img/2025/05/dr3-best-histogram.png&#34; width=&#34;90%&#34; style=&#34;width:90%;&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;decoding=&#34;async&#34; /&gt;&#xA;    &lt;/picture&gt;&lt;figcaption style=&#34;margin: 0 auto; width:90%;&#34;&gt;&#xA;            &lt;h4&gt;Magnitude distribution of Gaia DR3 Best catalog.&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;        &lt;/figcaption&gt;&#xA;&lt;/figure&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;details&gt;&#xA;  &lt;summary&gt;Click for raw data&lt;/summary&gt;&#xA;  &lt;div&gt;&lt;table&gt;&#xA;  &lt;thead&gt;&#xA;      &lt;tr&gt;&#xA;          &lt;th&gt;Magnitude&lt;/th&gt;&#xA;          &lt;th&gt;Count&lt;/th&gt;&#xA;          &lt;th&gt;Percentage&lt;/th&gt;&#xA;      &lt;/tr&gt;&#xA;  &lt;/thead&gt;&#xA;  &lt;tbody&gt;&#xA;      &lt;tr&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;0&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;20&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;0.003%&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;      &lt;/tr&gt;&#xA;      &lt;tr&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;49&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;0.007%&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;      &lt;/tr&gt;&#xA;      &lt;tr&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;257&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;0.034%&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;      &lt;/tr&gt;&#xA;      &lt;tr&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;994&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;0.133%&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;      &lt;/tr&gt;&#xA;      &lt;tr&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;3,347&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;0.449%&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;      &lt;/tr&gt;&#xA;      &lt;tr&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;5&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;9,839&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;1.319%&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;      &lt;/tr&gt;&#xA;      &lt;tr&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;6&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;27,198&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;3.647%&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;      &lt;/tr&gt;&#xA;      &lt;tr&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;7&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;60,012&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;8.046%&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;      &lt;/tr&gt;&#xA;      &lt;tr&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;8&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;90,040&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;12.072%&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;      &lt;/tr&gt;&#xA;      &lt;tr&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;9&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;91,461&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;12.263%&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;      &lt;/tr&gt;&#xA;      &lt;tr&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;10&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;107,119&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;14.362%&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;      &lt;/tr&gt;&#xA;      &lt;tr&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;11&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;152,413&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;20.435%&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;      &lt;/tr&gt;&#xA;      &lt;tr&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;12&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;199,507&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;26.750%&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;      &lt;/tr&gt;&#xA;      &lt;tr&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;13&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;3,546&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;0.475%&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;      &lt;/tr&gt;&#xA;      &lt;tr&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;14&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;5&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;0.001%&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;      &lt;/tr&gt;&#xA;      &lt;tr&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;15&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;2&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;0.000%&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;      &lt;/tr&gt;&#xA;      &lt;tr&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;16&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;0.000%&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;      &lt;/tr&gt;&#xA;      &lt;tr&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;17&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;11&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;0.001%&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;      &lt;/tr&gt;&#xA;      &lt;tr&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;18&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;4&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;0.001%&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;      &lt;/tr&gt;&#xA;      &lt;tr&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;19&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;3&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;0.000%&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;      &lt;/tr&gt;&#xA;      &lt;tr&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;20&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;0.000%&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;      &lt;/tr&gt;&#xA;      &lt;tr&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;21&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;1&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;          &lt;td&gt;0.000%&lt;/td&gt;&#xA;      &lt;/tr&gt;&#xA;  &lt;/tbody&gt;&#xA;&lt;/table&gt;&#xA;&lt;/div&gt;&#xA;&lt;/details&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;As expected, the catalog skews toward brighter stars with more accurate parallaxes.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;technical-notes&#34;&gt;Technical notes&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Catalog size: &lt;strong&gt;~54.5 MB&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Epoch: &lt;strong&gt;J2016&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Format: &lt;strong&gt;Gaia Sky binary octree&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Tree depth: &lt;strong&gt;1&lt;/strong&gt; (single octant for all stars)&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Max distance: &lt;strong&gt;100,000 parsecs&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;You can find the dataset under the key &lt;code&gt;gaia-dr3-best&lt;/code&gt; in the Gaia Sky catalog selector. The full path in disk is:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-bash&#34; data-lang=&#34;bash&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;$data/catalog-gaia-dr3-best&#xA;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Direct download: &lt;a href=&#34;https://gaia.ari.uni-heidelberg.de/gaiasky/files/repository/catalog/dr3/014-best/v01_20250530/&#34;&gt;Gaia DR3 Best Catalog&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;use-cases&#34;&gt;Use cases&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This catalog is especially suited for:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Running &lt;strong&gt;Gaia Sky&lt;/strong&gt; on lower-end machines without sacrificing precision&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Creating &lt;strong&gt;interactive educational content&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Building &lt;strong&gt;realistic local universe models&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Studying &lt;strong&gt;nearby star neighborhoods&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;figure class=&#34;fig-center vid-post&#34;&gt;&lt;video poster=&#34;https://gaiasky.space/vid/2025/dr3-best.jpg&#34; preload=&#34;none&#34;controls=&#34;controls&#34;&#xA;    &gt;&#xA;      &lt;source src=&#34;https://gaiasky.space/vid/2025/dr3-best.mp4&#34; autostart=&#34;false&#34;&gt;&#xA;        Your browser does not support the video tag.&#xA;    &lt;/video&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&#xA;            &lt;h4&gt;Short video showcasing the Gaia DR3 Best catalog in Gaia Sky.&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;        &lt;/figcaption&gt;&#xA;&lt;/figure&gt;</description>
      </item> 
      <item>
        <title>Performance boost in 3.6.8</title>
        <link>https://gaiasky.space/news/2025/performance-improvements/</link>
        <pubDate>Wed, 14 May 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid>https://gaiasky.space/news/2025/performance-improvements/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;The upcoming release of &lt;strong&gt;Gaia Sky 3.6.8&lt;/strong&gt; brings significant performance improvements, focusing on memory optimization and CPU usage reduction. In this post, we&amp;rsquo;ll take a closer look at these enhancements and how they translate into smoother and faster performance.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;memory-usage-optimization&#34;&gt;Memory Usage Optimization&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Gaia Sky 3.6.8 introduces multiple changes aimed at reducing memory footprint:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Quadruple Library Integration:&lt;/strong&gt; The &lt;code&gt;Apfloat&lt;/code&gt; library has been replaced with &lt;code&gt;Quadruple&lt;/code&gt;, a compact 128-bit floating point library that offers sufficient precision while minimizing memory allocations. It is also much faster! Find more details in &lt;a href=&#34;https://tonisagrista.com/blog/2025/quadruple-joins-party/&#34;&gt;this blog post&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Data Structure Refinement:&lt;/strong&gt; Particle data holders (for particle and star sets) are now flattened into Java records, consolidating several data structures and eliminating unnecessary attributes.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Memory Compaction:&lt;/strong&gt; The &lt;code&gt;PointCloudData&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;ParticleRecord&lt;/code&gt; classes have been refactored into compact records, reducing memory overhead.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;16-bit Floating Point Usage:&lt;/strong&gt; Non-critical attributes, such as star magnitudes, now use 16-bit precision, striking a balance between precision and memory consumption.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Below are the heap memory usage comparisons between Gaia Sky 3.6.7 (top) and 3.6.8 (bottom):&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&#xA;&lt;figure class=&#34;fig-center fig-post&#34;&gt;&lt;picture&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://gaiasky.space/img/2025/05/release-heap.svg&#34; width=&#34;80%&#34; style=&#34;width:80%;&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;decoding=&#34;async&#34; /&gt;&#xA;    &lt;/picture&gt;&lt;figcaption style=&#34;margin: 0 auto; width:80%;&#34;&gt;&#xA;            &lt;h4&gt;Heap memory usage for Gaia Sky 3.6.7 over a ~350 second session with the small Gaia DR3 dataset (~1.9 M stars loaded). Notice that the heap grows very fast and the garbage collector needs to act very often. The base memory usage sits at around 1.33 GB.&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;        &lt;/figcaption&gt;&#xA;&lt;/figure&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;figure class=&#34;fig-center fig-post&#34;&gt;&lt;picture&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://gaiasky.space/img/2025/05/master-heap.svg&#34; width=&#34;80%&#34; style=&#34;width:80%;&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;decoding=&#34;async&#34; /&gt;&#xA;    &lt;/picture&gt;&lt;figcaption style=&#34;margin: 0 auto; width:80%;&#34;&gt;&#xA;            &lt;h4&gt;Heap memory usage for Gaia Sky 3.6.8 over a ~350 second session with the small Gaia DR3 dataset (~2.5 M stars loaded). Minimizing allocations helps the heap grow super slowly, with a lower baseline of ~0.95 GB. Only two garbage collections were recorded during this session.&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;        &lt;/figcaption&gt;&#xA;&lt;/figure&gt;&#xA;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Note the much lower profile and drastically reduced garbage collector interventions (37 vs 2) in Gaia Sky 3.6.8. Observe that the allocated memory is now roughly half of what it used to be. Also, switching to the Generational ZGC caused the GC stops to go from ~10-100 ms to ~10 μs.  All this results in a higher latency, better memory utilization and more responsive experience.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;cpu-usage-reduction&#34;&gt;CPU Usage Reduction&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Several optimizations have been implemented to reduce CPU load and improve frame rates:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Custom Data Structures:&lt;/strong&gt; Gaia Sky now uses &lt;code&gt;FastObjectIntMap&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;FastStringObjectMap&lt;/code&gt; for the indices to eliminate the overhead of generic collections. This helps avoid allocating boxed &lt;code&gt;Integer&lt;/code&gt;s and &lt;code&gt;Node&lt;/code&gt;s, and perform much faster lookups.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Background Processing:&lt;/strong&gt; The background particle/star updater has been re-implemented from the ground up, leading to significant CPU savings.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Frame Distribution:&lt;/strong&gt; Metadata updates and sorting operations for star/particle sets are now spread across multiple frames to prevent frame spikes.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Generational ZGC:&lt;/strong&gt; The JRE has been upgraded to version 24, utilizing Generational ZGC by default. This modern garbage collector offers much shorter pauses and reduced latency.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Float-128 vs Apfloat:&lt;/strong&gt; One of the worse hot-spots in Gaia Sky has been the arbitrary floating-point arithmetic. So far, we&amp;rsquo;ve used &lt;code&gt;Apfloat&lt;/code&gt;. In this release, we switched to &lt;code&gt;Quadruple&lt;/code&gt;, a 128-float implementation that performs much &lt;a href=&#34;https://tonisagrista.com/blog/2025/quadruple-joins-party/&#34;&gt;faster&lt;/a&gt; that both &lt;code&gt;Apfloat&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;BigDecimal&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Here are the CPU usage comparisons using &lt;code&gt;btop&lt;/code&gt; for both versions:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&#xA;&lt;figure class=&#34;fig-center fig-post&#34;&gt;&lt;picture&gt;&#xA;      &lt;source srcset=&#34;https://gaiasky.space/img/2025/05/gs-cpu-3.6.7.avif&#34; type=&#34;image/avif&#34; /&gt;&#xA;      &#xA;      &lt;source srcset=&#34;https://gaiasky.space/img/2025/05/gs-cpu-3.6.7.jxl&#34; type=&#34;image/jxl&#34; /&gt;&#xA;      &lt;img src=&#34;https://gaiasky.space/img/2025/05/gs-cpu-3.6.7.jpg&#34; width=&#34;80%&#34; style=&#34;width:80%;&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;decoding=&#34;async&#34; /&gt;&#xA;    &lt;/picture&gt;&lt;figcaption style=&#34;margin: 0 auto; width:80%;&#34;&gt;&#xA;            &lt;h4&gt;CPU usage with Gaia Sky 3.6.7.&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;        &lt;/figcaption&gt;&#xA;&lt;/figure&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;figure class=&#34;fig-center fig-post&#34;&gt;&lt;picture&gt;&#xA;      &lt;source srcset=&#34;https://gaiasky.space/img/2025/05/gs-cpu-3.6.8.avif&#34; type=&#34;image/avif&#34; /&gt;&#xA;      &#xA;      &lt;source srcset=&#34;https://gaiasky.space/img/2025/05/gs-cpu-3.6.8.jxl&#34; type=&#34;image/jxl&#34; /&gt;&#xA;      &lt;img src=&#34;https://gaiasky.space/img/2025/05/gs-cpu-3.6.8.jpg&#34; width=&#34;80%&#34; style=&#34;width:80%;&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;decoding=&#34;async&#34; /&gt;&#xA;    &lt;/picture&gt;&lt;figcaption style=&#34;margin: 0 auto; width:80%;&#34;&gt;&#xA;            &lt;h4&gt;CPU usage with Gaia Sky 3.6.8.&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;        &lt;/figcaption&gt;&#xA;&lt;/figure&gt;&#xA;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Note the top image shows the CPU usage of Gaia Sky at 292%. This means that it is using 3 CPUs at full (the load is distributed between the 8 CPUs). At the bottom, I stopped version 3.6.7 and started version 3.6.8. You can see in the top pane the difference in CPU usage profile (annotated in red). The CPU usage sits at about 45% with Gaia Sky 3.6.8. A great improvement.&#xA;Curiously, and related to the previous section, the allocated memory in 3.6.7 sits at 6.2 GB, while it is below 3 GB in 3.6.8. The workload for both sessions was exactly the same, with the same datasets and settings.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The performance improvements in Gaia Sky 3.6.8 not only make it more memory-efficient but also significantly reduce CPU overhead. The result is a smoother and more responsive experience, particularly for systems dealing with large datasets or multiple particle/star sets.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Stay tuned for the official release and explore these enhancements firsthand!&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      </item> 
      <item>
        <title>New features in bookmarks</title>
        <link>https://gaiasky.space/news/2025/new-bookmarks/</link>
        <pubDate>Mon, 14 Apr 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid>https://gaiasky.space/news/2025/new-bookmarks/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;We’ve just leveled up bookmarks in Gaia Sky! As of the latest update, location bookmarks are no longer limited to just camera position, orientation, and time. Now, they can &lt;strong&gt;also store the full settings file&lt;/strong&gt; and the &lt;strong&gt;focus object&lt;/strong&gt; — giving you a complete snapshot of your session. Additionally, on creation the user may choose what elements to persist as part of the bookmark.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This means that when you load a bookmark, Gaia Sky can restore &lt;strong&gt;not only where you were&lt;/strong&gt;, but also &lt;strong&gt;how things were configured&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;what object you were focused on&lt;/strong&gt;. Whether you’re setting up a custom visualization, preparing a presentation, or just exploring the cosmos, your environment can now be fully restored with a single click.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;What’s more: all bookmark fields (except for the name) are now optional — you can selectively store in your bookmark only what matters to you.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;figure class=&#34;fig-center fig-post&#34;&gt;&lt;picture&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://gaiasky.space/img/2025/04/new-location-bookmark.jpg&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;decoding=&#34;async&#34; /&gt;&#xA;    &lt;/picture&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&#xA;            &lt;h4&gt;The new location bookmark dialog allows for the selection of the elements to persist.&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;        &lt;/figcaption&gt;&#xA;&lt;/figure&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;To learn more, check out the &lt;a href=&#34;https://gaia.ari.uni-heidelberg.de/gaiasky/docs/master/Bookmarks.html&#34;&gt;Bookmarks documentation&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The new feature will make it into the next Gaia Sky release. As always, you can already test it by &lt;a href=&#34;https://gaia.ari.uni-heidelberg.de/gaiasky/docs/master/Installation.html#run-from-source&#34;&gt;running Gaia Sky from source&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;</description>
      </item> 
      <item>
        <title>Towards smoother interstellar trips</title>
        <link>https://gaiasky.space/news/2025/smooth-interstellar-trips/</link>
        <pubDate>Thu, 20 Mar 2025 12:50:55 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid>https://gaiasky.space/news/2025/smooth-interstellar-trips/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;One of the items in our road map has long been the re-implementation of the speed scaling algorithm. This algorithm is a function that, given the current state of Gaia Sky, returns a number by which to scale the camera speed.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;So far, we have used a function that only takes into account the distance to the focus object (focus mode), or the distance to the closest object (any other mode). This does not work very well in many situations. In this post, I explore the new developments in Gaia Sky that enable smoother interstellar trips by means of the camera speed scaling.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-problem&#34;&gt;The problem&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The main issue with the current method is that its only dependency on the distance to the focus object makes it ignore all the (possibly closer to the camera) objects. We compute it like this,&#xA;$$&#xA;d_s = d_f * K,&#xA;$$&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;where \(d_s\) is the distance scale, \(d_f\) is the distance to the focus, and \(K\) is a constant.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Picture this: we are focused on Phobos in the Solar System, and the moon is in full view of our camera. In the background we spot an interesting star. We double-click on it to focus it, and then we click on the &amp;ldquo;Go to&amp;rdquo; button in the focus pane. With the current implementation, Phobos, Mars, and the entirety of the Solar System disappear in the first frame, because the first step towards our star focus is too large. This is because we are very far away from the star, and the speed scaling only depends on this distance. The speed is set to very high, so we are instantly thrown out of the Solar System.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;figure class=&#34;fig-center fig-post&#34;&gt;&lt;picture&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://gaiasky.space/img/2025/03/frames.svg&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;decoding=&#34;async&#34; /&gt;&#xA;    &lt;/picture&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&#xA;            &lt;h4&gt;The problem with the current speed scaling. Note how the first frame is already well outside the Solar System.&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;        &lt;/figcaption&gt;&#xA;&lt;/figure&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;How do we solve this?&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-solution&#34;&gt;The solution&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The first obvious solution is to &lt;em&gt;take into account objects other than the focus&lt;/em&gt;. One possible solution is to compute the local density of objects in an arbitrary volume around the camera, but this is probably overkill. Another solution might be setting up the closest object to the camera with a smoothing radius, and mix its distance with that of the focus:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;\begin{aligned}&#xA;d_s &amp;amp; = mix(d_c, d_f, a) \\&#xA;a &amp;amp; = \frac{d_c - d_0}{d_1 - d_0},&#xA;\end{aligned}&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;where \(d_c\) is the distance to the closest object, and \(d_0\) and \(d_1\) define the smoothing radius outer and inner bounds. When the camera is further away from the closest object than \(d_1\), only the focus distance is used. When  the camera is closer to the object than \(d_0\), only the distance to the closest object is use. In between the two smoothing distances, a mix of both is used.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;figure class=&#34;fig-center fig-post&#34;&gt;&lt;picture&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://gaiasky.space/img/2025/03/smoothing.svg&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;decoding=&#34;async&#34; /&gt;&#xA;    &lt;/picture&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&#xA;            &lt;h4&gt;The smoothing radius (in red and green) provides a smooth transition between using the distance to the focus and the distance to the closest object.&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;        &lt;/figcaption&gt;&#xA;&lt;/figure&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This method gives us a rather smooth transition from object to object. The camera is usually hooked to a single object, which may be the focus or the closest object. In the case that the camera is between \(d_0\) and \(d_1\) from the closest object, we mix the contributions to avoid stark transitions in speed.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The video below compares the old and the new methods:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;figure class=&#34;fig-center vid-post&#34;&gt;&lt;video poster=&#34;https://gaiasky.space/vid/2025/speed-scaling-comparison.jpg&#34; preload=&#34;none&#34;controls=&#34;controls&#34;&#xA;    &gt;&#xA;      &lt;source src=&#34;https://gaiasky.space/vid/2025/speed-scaling-comparison.mp4&#34; autostart=&#34;false&#34;&gt;&#xA;        Your browser does not support the video tag.&#xA;    &lt;/video&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&#xA;            &lt;h4&gt;Comparison between the old method, based on focus distance, and the new method, that takes into account other objects.&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;        &lt;/figcaption&gt;&#xA;&lt;/figure&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;transition-based-trips&#34;&gt;Transition-based trips&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;https://gaia.ari.uni-heidelberg.de/gaiasky/docs/javadoc/latest/gaiasky/script/IScriptingInterface.html&#34;&gt;Gaia Sky API&lt;/a&gt; contains some methods to create frame-accurate camera transitions in both position and orientation. Those are smooth by design, as they can use &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Logit&#34;&gt;logit&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Logistic_function&#34;&gt;logistic sigmoid&lt;/a&gt; mapping functions.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;These methods interpolate the camera state (position, direction, and up vectors) from the current state to a user-defined final state. They do so in a provided amount of time, and using the provided mapping function. They end up calling something like this:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;div class=&#34;highlight&#34;&gt;&lt;pre tabindex=&#34;0&#34; style=&#34;color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;&#34;&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-java&#34; data-lang=&#34;java&#34;&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;void&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span style=&#34;color:#a6e22e&#34;&gt;cameraTransition&lt;/span&gt;(&lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;double&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;[]&lt;/span&gt; camPos,&#xA;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;                       String units,&#xA;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;                       &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;double&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;[]&lt;/span&gt; camDir,&#xA;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;                       &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;double&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;color:#f92672&#34;&gt;[]&lt;/span&gt; camUp,&#xA;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;                       &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;double&lt;/span&gt; positionDurationSeconds,&#xA;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;                       String positionSmoothType,&#xA;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;                       &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;double&lt;/span&gt; positionSmoothFactor,&#xA;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;                       &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;double&lt;/span&gt; orientationDurationSeconds,&#xA;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;                       String orientationSmoothType,&#xA;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;                       &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;double&lt;/span&gt; orientationSmoothFactor,&#xA;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style=&#34;display:flex;&#34;&gt;&lt;span&gt;                       &lt;span style=&#34;color:#66d9ef&#34;&gt;boolean&lt;/span&gt; sync)&#xA;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://gaia.ari.uni-heidelberg.de/gaiasky/docs/javadoc/latest/gaiasky/script/IScriptingInterface.html#cameraTransition(double%5B%5D,java.lang.String,double%5B%5D,double%5B%5D,double,java.lang.String,double,double,java.lang.String,double,boolean)&#34;&gt;Here&lt;/a&gt; is the documentation. For completion, the parameters are as follows:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;camPos&lt;/code&gt; &amp;ndash; final camera position.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;units&lt;/code&gt; &amp;ndash; final camera position units.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;camDir&lt;/code&gt; &amp;ndash; final camera direction vector.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;camUp&lt;/code&gt; &amp;ndash; final camera up vector.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;positionDurationSeconds&lt;/code&gt; &amp;ndash; duration of transition in position, in seconds.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;positionSmoothType&lt;/code&gt; &amp;ndash; mapping function, either &amp;ldquo;logisticsigmoid&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;logit&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;positionSmoothFactor&lt;/code&gt; &amp;ndash; smoothing factor for the mapping function.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;orientationDurationSeconds&lt;/code&gt; &amp;ndash; duration of the transition in orientation, in seconds.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;orientationSmoothType&lt;/code&gt; &amp;ndash; mapping function, either &amp;ldquo;logisticsigmoid&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;logit&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;orientationSmoothFactor&lt;/code&gt; &amp;ndash; smoothing factor for the mapping function.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;sync&lt;/code&gt; &amp;ndash; whether to run in synchronous mode, or return immediately and run asynchronously.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;smooth-go-to-object-api-call&#34;&gt;Smooth go-to-object API call&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Since we already have the &lt;code&gt;goToObject(name)&lt;/code&gt; API call, which uses the regular speed scaling-based method described in the previous sections, I thought I would take advantage of the already implemented transitions and spin up a &lt;em&gt;better&lt;/em&gt; go-to. I called it &lt;code&gt;goToObjectSmooth(name, posDuration, orientationDuration)&lt;/code&gt; [&lt;a href=&#34;https://gaia.ari.uni-heidelberg.de/gaiasky/docs/javadoc/latest/gaiasky/script/IScriptingInterface.html#goToObjectSmooth(java.lang.String,double,double)&#34;&gt;API reference&lt;/a&gt;]. This method uses camera transitions internally, and produces a fundamentally different result than its plain &lt;code&gt;goToObject()&lt;/code&gt; counterpart. I happen to think that produces better results in most cases.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Here is a comparison video with both methods.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;figure class=&#34;fig-center vid-post&#34;&gt;&lt;video poster=&#34;https://gaiasky.space/vid/2025/goto-smooth.jpg&#34; preload=&#34;none&#34;controls=&#34;controls&#34;&#xA;    &gt;&#xA;      &lt;source src=&#34;https://gaiasky.space/vid/2025/goto-smooth.mp4&#34; autostart=&#34;false&#34;&gt;&#xA;        Your browser does not support the video tag.&#xA;    &lt;/video&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&#xA;            &lt;h4&gt;The new goToObjectSmooth() API call produces a more pleasant trip from start to finish.&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;        &lt;/figcaption&gt;&#xA;&lt;/figure&gt;</description>
      </item> 
      <item>
        <title>Gaia Sky 3.6.7</title>
        <link>https://gaiasky.space/news/2025/gaiasky_3.6.7/</link>
        <pubDate>Tue, 18 Mar 2025 13:20:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid>https://gaiasky.space/news/2025/gaiasky_3.6.7/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;📢 We are happy to announce the release of Gaia Sky 3.6.7. This release comes with a few minor features and many important bug fixes, especially related to VR and scripting.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;features&#34;&gt;Features&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Add composition of timed orbit coordinates and timed orbit coordinates to enable changing orbits during an object&amp;rsquo;s lifetime.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Update app colors in metainfo file.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Update metainfo with better screenshots, appropriately sized for Flathub.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Update icons to higher resolution, add macOS and round versions.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Update pointers to project website and docs.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Add script to test frame output.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Add instructions to new website in release script.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Adjust star shader so that sunspots are more prominent. Enable hot reload in star shaders (use &lt;code&gt;Ctrl&lt;/code&gt;+&lt;code&gt;Shift&lt;/code&gt;+&lt;code&gt;Y&lt;/code&gt;).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Remove music classes and events.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Increase default line width of recursive grid.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;bug-fixes&#34;&gt;Bug Fixes&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Star velocity vectors in VR do not work.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Star&amp;rsquo;s proper motions do not work in VR.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;stopRecordingCameraPath()&lt;/code&gt; does not work.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Default to &amp;lsquo;.jpg&amp;rsquo; instead of &amp;lsquo;.jpeg&amp;rsquo; as file extension for screenshots and still frames.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Refreshing orbits sometimes crashes the thread.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Constellation names sometimes not showing up with LOD catalogs.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;FORCE_OBJECT_LABEL_CMD&lt;/code&gt; now accepts an &lt;code&gt;Entity&lt;/code&gt; type to work with &lt;code&gt;setForceDisplayLabel(name)&lt;/code&gt; API call.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Adjust recursive grid labels and base model size.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Billboard rendering for single stars in VR mode.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Do not show component types with no style in visibility component or game pad GUI.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Focus orientation lock does not work consistently.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Trajectory scaling.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Missing translation keys for invisible component type.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Restore motion blur settings crashes the app.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Changelog template contains wrong URL paths.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;code-refactoring&#34;&gt;Code Refactoring&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Clean up skins, remove unused icons.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;build-system&#34;&gt;Build System&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Upgrade to Gradle 8.10.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Remove old downloads-table template, update release script with new instructions regarding release publishing on the new gaiasky.space website.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Include metainfo file in tarball, Flathub now requires this file to come from upstream.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Remove 16 and 32 pixel icons from launchers. Use only 128 pixels for macOS.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;documentation&#34;&gt;Documentation&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Update website pointers in README file.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;As always, you can grab it in the &lt;a href=&#34;https://gaiasky.space/downloads/&#34;&gt;downloads page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      </item> 
      <item>
        <title>Moon 32K topography virtual texture</title>
        <link>https://gaiasky.space/news/2025/moon-vt-32k/</link>
        <pubDate>Tue, 18 Feb 2025 09:15:20 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid>https://gaiasky.space/news/2025/moon-vt-32k/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;We&amp;rsquo;d like to announce that we just published a new virtual texture dataset. This dataset is based on NASA&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;https://svs.gsfc.nasa.gov/4720&#34;&gt;Scientific Visualization Studio CGI Moon Kit&lt;/a&gt;. Constructed from the DEM (Digital Elevation Map) in LRO/LOLA, it contains a 32K virtual texture for the Moon topography (elevation). When you have tessellation activated, this represents elevation in the Moon by vertex displacement and subdivision.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;figure class=&#34;fig-center fig-post&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://gaiasky.space/img/2025/02/32k-vt-moon.jpg&#34;&gt;&lt;picture&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://gaiasky.space/img/2025/02/32k-vt-moon.thumb.jpg&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;decoding=&#34;async&#34; /&gt;&#xA;    &lt;/picture&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&#xA;            &lt;h4&gt;The new 32K topography virtual texture applied to the Moon in Gaia Sky.&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;        &lt;/figcaption&gt;&#xA;&lt;/figure&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;You can get it from the &lt;strong&gt;dataset manager&lt;/strong&gt; in Gaia Sky. Just look up &amp;ldquo;32K Moon Topography&amp;rdquo; and it should just pop right up.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The repository for this dataset is &lt;a href=&#34;https://codeberg.org/gaiasky/gsdata-vt-moon-topography-nasa&#34;&gt;codeberg.org/gaiasky/gsdata-vt-moon-topography-nasa&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Original &lt;a href=&#34;https://svs.gsfc.nasa.gov/4720#section_credits&#34;&gt;credits&lt;/a&gt; go to Ernie Wright (USRA) and Noah Petro (NASA/GSFC).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      </item> 
      <item>
        <title>New Flatpak app ID</title>
        <link>https://gaiasky.space/news/2025/new-flatpak-id/</link>
        <pubDate>Fri, 14 Feb 2025 09:00:20 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid>https://gaiasky.space/news/2025/new-flatpak-id/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Our Flatpak package, published via &lt;a href=&#34;https://flathub.org&#34;&gt;Flathub&lt;/a&gt;, has been updated to a new app ID &lt;a href=&#34;https://flathub.org/apps/space.gaiasky.GaiaSky&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;space.gaiasky.GaiaSky&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. This has been done to match the domain of our new website &lt;a href=&#34;https://gaiasky.space&#34;&gt;gaiasky.space&lt;/a&gt;. Additionally, this has enabled us to verify the application, which was impossible with the old &lt;code&gt;de.uni_heidelberg.zah.GaiaSky&lt;/code&gt; ID, as we did not control that domain.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;figure class=&#34;fig-center fig-post&#34;&gt;&lt;picture&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://gaiasky.space/img/2025/02/flathub.jpg&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;decoding=&#34;async&#34; /&gt;&#xA;    &lt;/picture&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&#xA;            &lt;h4&gt;Gaia Sky is now verified on Flathub.&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;        &lt;/figcaption&gt;&#xA;&lt;/figure&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Essentially, I needed to contact the &lt;a href=&#34;https://uni-heidelberg.de&#34;&gt;uni-heidelberg.de&lt;/a&gt; domain owner and ask them to add their domain to a PSL (public suffix list). They were initially cooperative, but after a few department redirections my requests must have fallen down the bureaucracy cracks, for they stopped being responsive. If you want the full story, check out &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/flathub/de.uni_heidelberg.zah.GaiaSky/issues/57&#34;&gt;this issue&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/flathub-infra/website/issues/3844&#34;&gt;this one&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Anyway, creating a proper website for Gaia Sky was already on the to-do list. In fact, the  initial commit to the project was made &lt;a href=&#34;https://codeberg.org/gaiasky/gaiasky-web/commit/61d9802b4d9506920d53411a8e722062f2ef7eaf&#34;&gt;a long time ago&lt;/a&gt;. Almost exactly 4 years ago, to be precise.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;</description>
      </item> 
      <item>
        <title>New homepage</title>
        <link>https://gaiasky.space/news/2025/new-site/</link>
        <pubDate>Fri, 31 Jan 2025 09:41:55 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid>https://gaiasky.space/news/2025/new-site/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Today we publish the new Gaia Sky web site. If you are reading this, you obviously know it. I&amp;rsquo;ve been working on this for a while, and, even though it is not yet finished, I think it is now ready to be deployed. Until now, we have used the website of &lt;a href=&#34;https://zah.ari.uni-heidelberg.de&#34;&gt;our institute&lt;/a&gt;, which uses the Typo3 CMS, as our home page. In a few days, I&amp;rsquo;ll make it point to this new site.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;It is easier to add content to, and easier to maintain. I also happen to think it looks better. I hope you enjoy it.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The canonical URL, for now, is this:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://gaiasky.space&#34;&gt;https://gaiasky.space&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;</description>
      </item> 
      <item>
        <title>Gaia Sky 3.6.6</title>
        <link>https://gaiasky.space/news/2025/gaiasky_3.6.6/</link>
        <pubDate>Fri, 24 Jan 2025 09:41:55 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid>https://gaiasky.space/news/2025/gaiasky_3.6.6/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;📢 Today we publish the version 3.6.6 of Gaia Sky. This is a small update focused on fixing some bugs and improving performance. Also, it comes with proper handling of depth for volumes!&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;figure class=&#34;fig-center vid-post&#34;&gt;&lt;video poster=&#34;https://gaiasky.space/vid/2025/3.6.6-release.jpg&#34; preload=&#34;none&#34;controls=&#34;controls&#34;&#xA;    &gt;&#xA;      &lt;source src=&#34;https://gaiasky.space/vid/2025/3.6.6-release.mp4&#34; autostart=&#34;false&#34;&gt;&#xA;        Your browser does not support the video tag.&#xA;    &lt;/video&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&#xA;            &lt;h4&gt;The Trifid nebula (NGC6514) rendered as a volume with correct usage of the depth buffer.&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;        &lt;/figcaption&gt;&#xA;&lt;/figure&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;features&#34;&gt;Features&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Move volumes earlier in the rendering pipeline, because they now write to the depth buffer.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Check for dataset incompatibilities and ask user to confirm action when selecting incompatible datasets.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Add window size and resolution of external view in settings, when the external view is active.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;bug-fixes&#34;&gt;Bug Fixes&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Attitude indicator not scaling with units-per-pixel value in spacecraft UI.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Incorrect initialization of label threshold in volumes in VR mode.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Entering panorama mode resets back-buffer scale. The issue was that the dynamic resolution reset routine was always applied, and not only when the dynamic resolution setting was on.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;performance-improvements&#34;&gt;Performance Improvements&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Replace arbitrary precision &lt;code&gt;add()&lt;/code&gt; call with double-precision one to compute spherical coordinates of objects. Double-precision is more than sufficient for that purpose.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;build-system&#34;&gt;Build System&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Update install4j template to version 11.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;documentation&#34;&gt;Documentation&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Improve javadoc comments in settings class.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;As always, you can grab it in the &lt;a href=&#34;https://gaiasky.space/downloads/&#34;&gt;downloads page&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      </item> 
      <item>
        <title>Gaia Sky 3.6.5</title>
        <link>https://gaiasky.space/news/2025/gaiasky_3.6.5/</link>
        <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2025 09:41:55 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid>https://gaiasky.space/news/2025/gaiasky_3.6.5/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;📢 Today, coinciding with the end of the sky-scanning phase of Gaia, we publish Gaia Sky 3.6.5. The most noteworthy addition is the introduction of the volume rendering infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;figure class=&#34;fig-center fig-post&#34;&gt;&lt;picture&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://gaiasky.space/img/2025/01/3.6.5-release.jpg&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;decoding=&#34;async&#34; /&gt;&#xA;    &lt;/picture&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&#xA;            &lt;h4&gt;Gaia Sky 3.6.5 welcome screen.&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;        &lt;/figcaption&gt;&#xA;&lt;/figure&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;features&#34;&gt;Features&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Add support for volume rendering. The infrastructure is in place with a new archetype &lt;code&gt;Volume&lt;/code&gt;. This is necessary for the new volumetric aurora dataset and volume nebulae in NGC2000.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Add &amp;lsquo;volumes and effects&amp;rsquo; catalog type.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Enable &lt;code&gt;&amp;quot;flip&amp;quot;&lt;/code&gt; attribute for &lt;code&gt;box&lt;/code&gt;es/&lt;code&gt;cube&lt;/code&gt;s in mesh builders.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Add &lt;code&gt;&amp;quot;cameraCollision&amp;quot;&lt;/code&gt; attribute to bodies.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Shader include statement now supports targets in datasets.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Add on-demand re-compilation of post-processing shaders from their source files, in runtime.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Add new attribute &lt;code&gt;renderLabel&lt;/code&gt; to label component. This enables/disables the actual rendering of the label.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Increase default quality of FXAA filter, provide a simpler implementation (disabled by default), and enable hot shader reloading for FXAA effect.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Update Gaia Sky icon.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Add Bluesky link to readme file and about page.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;bug-fixes&#34;&gt;Bug Fixes&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Position of context menu in dataset manager is off.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Unknown dataset types crash Gaia Sky. Fixes &lt;a href=&#34;https://codeberg.org/gaiasky/gaiasky/issues/787&#34;&gt;#787&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Do not crash when reloading non-compiling glsl shaders.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Wrong size initialization for ray-marched objects.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Prevent non-focusable objects to appear in search results and to be set as camera focus.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Enable atmosphere/cloud procedural generation even when the surface is disabled due to cubemaps being used.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Do not attempt setting a window icon in Wayland, it is not supported and results in a (harmless) crash.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Position tracking does not work with objects in orbital elements group.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Correctly populate window width and height in preferences dialog.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;build-system&#34;&gt;Build System&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Update configuration file version number. This implies that your old configuration file gets overridden with the new version during the first startup of the new Gaia Sky version.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Update to LibGDX 1.13.1.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;As always, you can grab it &lt;a href=&#34;https://gaiasky.space/downloads/&#34;&gt;right here&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;a href=&#34;https://gaia.ari.uni-heidelberg.de/gaiasky/releases/3.6.5.a7ae14f4d&#34;&gt;link to repository&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      </item> 
      <item>
        <title>Gaia Sky 3.6.4-2</title>
        <link>https://gaiasky.space/news/2024/gaiasky_3.6.4-2/</link>
        <pubDate>Thu, 17 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid>https://gaiasky.space/news/2024/gaiasky_3.6.4-2/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;📢 Gaia Sky patch release 3.6.4-2 includes a fix for the external view feature.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;bug-fixes&#34;&gt;Bug Fixes&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;External view feature not working.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;build-system&#34;&gt;Build System&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Remove lib directory, does not contain anything anymore.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;As always, you can grab it &lt;a href=&#34;https://gaiasky.space/downloads/&#34;&gt;right here&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;a href=&#34;https://gaia.ari.uni-heidelberg.de/gaiasky/releases/3.6.4-2.3bfeec0f9&#34;&gt;link to repository&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      </item> 
      <item>
        <title>Gaia Sky 3.6.4</title>
        <link>https://gaiasky.space/news/2024/gaiasky_3.6.4/</link>
        <pubDate>Tue, 08 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid>https://gaiasky.space/news/2024/gaiasky_3.6.4/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;📢 Gaia Sky 3.6.4 released! It comes with a new in-app console, a revamp in the locations feature, and some under-the-hood rendering improvements.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;figure class=&#34;fig-center fig-post&#34;&gt;&lt;picture&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://gaiasky.space/img/2024/10/3.6.4/3.6.4-release.jpg&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;decoding=&#34;async&#34; /&gt;&#xA;    &lt;/picture&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&#xA;            &lt;h4&gt;Gaia Sky 3.6.4 welcome screen.&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;        &lt;/figcaption&gt;&#xA;&lt;/figure&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;features&#34;&gt;Features&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Add location markers to pinpoint the exact position of each location. Add custom marker textures and custom label and marker colors.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Add new attribute to locations, &lt;code&gt;ignoreSolidAngleLimit&lt;/code&gt;, which disregards the limits when computing visibility. Cap angular sizes for all locations.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Add location type attribute to location objects. This attribute is used to categorize locations by groups in the individual visibility window. Remove &amp;lsquo;cosmic locations&amp;rsquo; content type, and move it to regular locations (requires default data pack update.).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Separate scene frame buffer from meta-elements rendering (labels, lines, etc.) to be able to apply different post-processing effects to each.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Add an implementation of console/terminal, which accepts commands to interact directly with the Gaia Sky API. Use &lt;code&gt;~&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;:&lt;/code&gt; to launch the console.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Add a generic map in the base component to store &amp;lsquo;unrecognized&amp;rsquo; attributes; these get displayed in the object info window.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Improve on-screen keyboard in controller UI.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Add session type (X11, Wayland) to system information (Linux only).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;figure class=&#34;fig-center fig-post&#34;&gt;&lt;picture&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://gaiasky.space//img/2024/10/3.6.4/3.6.4-markers.jpg&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;decoding=&#34;async&#34; /&gt;&#xA;    &lt;/picture&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&#xA;            &lt;h4&gt;The new markers on the Moon.&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;        &lt;/figcaption&gt;&#xA;&lt;/figure&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;bug-fixes&#34;&gt;Bug Fixes&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Prevent virtual objects (hooks, invisibles, catalogs, etc.) from appearing in the individual visibility window. Hide meta-components (atmospheres, key frames, etc.) from buttons list. Fix layout.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Always load HIP numbers if present in the STIL data loader, even if there are other identifiers.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Update jEtty, JSON and XMLRPC libraries to secure versions (the old versions contain known vulnerabilities).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Inform user of unsupported cubemap textured objects with procedural generation.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;build-system&#34;&gt;Build System&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Update versions of &lt;code&gt;jCommander&lt;/code&gt;, STIL and &lt;code&gt;Apfloat&lt;/code&gt;, remove &lt;code&gt;Joise&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Update OSHI library version.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;figure class=&#34;fig-center fig-post&#34;&gt;&lt;picture&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://gaiasky.space//img/2024/10/3.6.4/3.6.4-console.jpg&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;decoding=&#34;async&#34; /&gt;&#xA;    &lt;/picture&gt;&lt;figcaption&gt;&#xA;            &lt;h4&gt;The console allows direct interaction with the API.&lt;/h4&gt;&#xA;        &lt;/figcaption&gt;&#xA;&lt;/figure&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;documentation&#34;&gt;Documentation&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Add architectures to download table.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Fix typos and spelling errors in changelog file.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Move VR info into README.md from VR.md.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;As always, you can grab it &lt;a href=&#34;https://gaiasky.space/downloads/&#34;&gt;right here&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;a href=&#34;https://gaia.ari.uni-heidelberg.de/gaiasky/releases/3.6.4-2.3bfeec0f9&#34;&gt;link to repository&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      </item> 
      <item>
        <title>Gaia Sky 3.6.3-2</title>
        <link>https://gaiasky.space/news/2024/gaiasky_3.6.3-2/</link>
        <pubDate>Wed, 17 Jul 2024 10:44:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid>https://gaiasky.space/news/2024/gaiasky_3.6.3-2/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;📢 Gaia Sky 3.6.3-2 available now!&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;features&#34;&gt;Features&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Use noise library for star surface shader.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;bug-fixes&#34;&gt;Bug Fixes&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Bad truncation leads to some SVTs not working properly. Fixes &lt;a href=&#34;https://codeberg.org/gaiasky/gaiasky/issues/778&#34;&gt;#778&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;You can get this release in &lt;a href=&#34;https://gaia.ari.uni-heidelberg.de/gaiasky/releases//3.6.3-2.5dd63b3c7/&#34;&gt;our repository&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      </item> 
      <item>
        <title>Gaia Sky 3.6.3</title>
        <link>https://gaiasky.space/news/2024/gaiasky_3.6.3/</link>
        <pubDate>Fri, 12 Jul 2024 11:10:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid>https://gaiasky.space/news/2024/gaiasky_3.6.3/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;📢 Gaia Sky 3.6.3 available now!&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;features&#34;&gt;Features&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Add on-demand loading of JSON datasets to particle groups, which enables having thousands of extrasolar systems to explore.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Add script to translate a NASA exoplanet archive VOTable to the Gaia Sky JSON format.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Replace CPU-based procedural generation with GPU-based implementation, which is orders of magnitude faster.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Improve layout of procedural generation window.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Improve cloud color and atmospheric fog density randomizers.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Use normal map when elevation type is &amp;lsquo;None&amp;rsquo; in procedural generation.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Add initial amplitude to noise parametrization in procedural generation.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Surface generation presets (Earth-like, gas giant, rocky planet, etc.), and hide noise parameters in collapsible pane.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Add procedurally generated texture resolution to configuration and preferences window.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Add procedural generation button to camera info interface.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Move &amp;lsquo;save textures&amp;rsquo; of procedural generation to a parallel thread.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Divide procedural generation in 4 consecutive frames. Add emission generation as an extra (optional) channel.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Add &amp;lsquo;systems&amp;rsquo; component type, to contain all extrasolar planetary systems.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Automatic DPI scaling to support multi-DPI configurations.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Add new graphical presets (low, medium, high) to settings dialog. These presets are sets of settings that are applied all at once.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Change antialiasing settings from only type to type and quality in the configuration file.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Add tooltip with hotkeys to cinematic camera checkbox.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Improve camera velocity display units in camera info pane.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;New splash image based on NASA exoplanets.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Enable multiple lights (and also point lights) for cloud shader. This is necessary for the NASA exoplanets.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Add &amp;lsquo;refreshRate&amp;rsquo; to orbit objects to control how often they are updated (if needed), add button to camera info interface to refresh the orbit of the selected object.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;bug-fixes&#34;&gt;Bug Fixes&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Relativistic shaders define their own helper functions.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Broken anchor in readme file.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Error computing next focus and closest body positions.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Restore elevation-aware planet traversal.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Artifacts in atmosphere shader when SSR is active.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Adjust maximum reach of point lights.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Improve single star selection code, especially when close to stars.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Regression where orientation lock stopped working altogether.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Adjust frequency and lacunarity randomizers so that more strucutre is always present.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Crash during initialization when model is set to randomize.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Tooltip background width incorrectly computed.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Remove call to pack() in constructor.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;performance-improvements&#34;&gt;Performance Improvements&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Enable fast-math usage by default, and remove old, unused trigo scaffolding classes.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Improve performance of recursive grid shader, which was very slow due to the background fill (with interpolation), and the animation. Animation is now removed.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;build-system&#34;&gt;Build System&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Upgrade bundled JRE to 21, minimum language version to 17.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;You can get this release in &lt;a href=&#34;https://gaia.ari.uni-heidelberg.de/gaiasky/releases//3.6.3.929b0f7a6/&#34;&gt;our repository&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      </item> 
      <item>
        <title>Gaia Sky 3.6.2-3</title>
        <link>https://gaiasky.space/news/2024/gaiasky_3.6.2-3/</link>
        <pubDate>Fri, 07 Jun 2024 09:26:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid>https://gaiasky.space/news/2024/gaiasky_3.6.2-3/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;📢 Gaia Sky 3.6.2-3 available now!&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;bug-fixes&#34;&gt;Bug Fixes&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;SVT indirection shader cleared with wrong value. Fixes &lt;a href=&#34;https://codeberg.org/gaiasky/gaiasky/issues/774&#34;&gt;#774&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;You can get this release in &lt;a href=&#34;https://gaia.ari.uni-heidelberg.de/gaiasky/releases//3.6.2-3.d5632974f/&#34;&gt;our repository&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      </item> 
      <item>
        <title>Gaia Sky 3.6.2-2</title>
        <link>https://gaiasky.space/news/2024/gaiasky_3.6.2-2/</link>
        <pubDate>Thu, 06 Jun 2024 09:06:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid>https://gaiasky.space/news/2024/gaiasky_3.6.2-2/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;📢 Gaia Sky 3.6.2-2 available now!&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;bug-fixes&#34;&gt;Bug Fixes&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Shadow map GLSL library crash due to use of old, unsupported  call. Fixes &lt;a href=&#34;https://codeberg.org/gaiasky/gaiasky/issues/773&#34;&gt;#773&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;You can get this release in &lt;a href=&#34;https://gaia.ari.uni-heidelberg.de/gaiasky/releases//3.6.2-2.c12559806/&#34;&gt;our repository&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      </item> 
      <item>
        <title>Gaia Sky 3.6.2</title>
        <link>https://gaiasky.space/news/2024/gaiasky_3.6.2/</link>
        <pubDate>Wed, 05 Jun 2024 15:27:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid>https://gaiasky.space/news/2024/gaiasky_3.6.2/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;📢 Gaia Sky 3.6.2 available now!&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;features&#34;&gt;Features&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Enable ray-marching effects in stereoscopic mode.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;bug-fixes&#34;&gt;Bug Fixes&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Use a new instance of the preferences dialog each time it is open, so that all preferences are reinitialized correctly.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Invert-x/-y button in gamepad GUI does not work/update correctly.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Ray-marching effects in cubemap modes. Probably a source of unforeseen consequences.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Remove blank frame produced when activating a ray-marching effect for the first time.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Never skip future closest body position computation.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Restore light glow effect in cubemap modes (360, planetarium, orthosphere).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Restore light glow effect in stereoscopic mode.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;You can get this release in &lt;a href=&#34;https://gaia.ari.uni-heidelberg.de/gaiasky/releases//3.6.2.1b1e23dbb/&#34;&gt;our repository&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      </item> 
      <item>
        <title>Gaia Sky 3.6.1</title>
        <link>https://gaiasky.space/news/2024/gaiasky_3.6.1/</link>
        <pubDate>Wed, 29 May 2024 11:54:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid>https://gaiasky.space/news/2024/gaiasky_3.6.1/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;📢 Gaia Sky 3.6.1 available now!&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;features&#34;&gt;Features&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Add input debug mode where all input events from input devices are logged to the info channel.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Move camera and keyframes files times from long to ISO-8601 (&amp;lsquo;2011-12-03T10:15:30Z&amp;rsquo;), which is more readable. Add quaternion slerp orientation server, based on text files.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Derive model span from vertex and transformation data instead of relying on values in the descriptor files.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Add spectral type to camera info interface, computed for stars from the effective temperature.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Add &amp;lsquo;saturation&amp;rsquo; value to settings (under stars) to control the star saturation factor.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Display effective temperature of body in camera info interface.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Camera motion blur re-implementation using a pure post-processing approach, where the pixel positions are reconstructed from the depth buffer and the current and previous camera states. This does not require the velocity buffer anymore, so it is much faster. Add motion blur slider to regular and gamepad preferences.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Add LVLH (local vertical local horizontal) attitude server, for objects like the ISS.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Add support for gzipped streams in orbit file data provider.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Add label bias attribute to label component to provide a way to artificially move the point at which the object&amp;rsquo;s label is rendered.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Add &amp;lsquo;periodic&amp;rsquo; attribute to orbit coordinates objects.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Improve UV grids so that their line width stays constant, they get subdivided when changing the field of view, and they get coordinates on the window frame.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Improve recursive grid with constant-width lines and better distance value labels.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Enable label rendering for invisibles, if labels are active for the object.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Add option to display the time in no-UI mode (enter with Ctrl+U), and add checkbox to toggle setting in preferences dialog.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Add support for binary file-backed VSOP87, and update data files. Needs update of base data package. Add versioning to bookmarks file.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Add display information to help window, system tab.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Add script to test object quaternion slerp provider.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Add script to test camera orientation API calls that use quaternions.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;bug-fixes&#34;&gt;Bug Fixes&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Prevent activation of stereoscopic mode in VR.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Position bookmarks do not work in VR.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Check type of current model in gamepad GUI.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Unescape HTML4.0 strings in wikipedia snippet title and body.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Only load spacecraft GUI when the default data pack is there. Otherwise, the system crashes.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Crash when the server response is not in JSON format, due to the server being down.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;REST server parameters matching does not check that the number of parameters is correct during matching.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Warn about trying to bind reserved ports (&amp;lt;1024).&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Star absolute magnitude derivation.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Land-at-location parameter check.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Problem with shadow map frame buffers that sometimes corrupted shadows when two or more objects were in scene.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Move initialization of derived particle attributes to the set-up stage, as it needs the coordinates object to be in place.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Orientation lock with quaternion-based objects.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Use color alpha channel to scale transparency in models.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Optflowcam script to use formatted times.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Use own parser to convert keyframe times. Fixes &lt;a href=&#34;https://codeberg.org/gaiasky/gaiasky/issues/768&#34;&gt;#768&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Prevent index retrieval in particle sets while the index is being generated or updated.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Initial determination of screen size and UI scale factor.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Initial fetch of screen size in macOS, attempt a method involving graphics device and max window bounds that should work with macOS.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;performance-improvements&#34;&gt;Performance Improvements&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Substitute commons-compress with jtar, saving ~2 MB of space.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Reduce size of skin and image files.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Adapt number of labels in octree star sets according to current octant view angle. Add fast linear interpolator functions that skips some checks, for cases where we can guarantee that x0 &amp;lt;= x1.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Speed up star position computation (for labels and billboards), cap number of labels per octree star group, reduce precision of arbitrary precision numbers. These measures result in a drastic increase in overall performance.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;code-refactoring&#34;&gt;Code Refactoring&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Shadow mapping shaders rearranged, fix shadow blending in PBR fragment shader to work well with atmosphere ground colors.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Rename post-processing filters for consistency.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;documentation&#34;&gt;Documentation&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Update OptFlowCam reference.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Complete library acknowledgements.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Add descriptions for all custom gradle tasks.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;You can get this release in &lt;a href=&#34;https://gaia.ari.uni-heidelberg.de/gaiasky/releases//3.6.1.f3a379a3d/&#34;&gt;our repository&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      </item> 
      <item>
        <title>Gaia Sky 3.6.0-3</title>
        <link>https://gaiasky.space/news/2024/gaiasky_3.6.0-3/</link>
        <pubDate>Fri, 15 Mar 2024 20:26:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid>https://gaiasky.space/news/2024/gaiasky_3.6.0-3/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;📢 Gaia Sky 3.6.0-3 available now!&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;bug-fixes&#34;&gt;Bug Fixes&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Back-buffer scale initialization when config file is resetted.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;You can get this release in &lt;a href=&#34;https://gaia.ari.uni-heidelberg.de/gaiasky/releases//3.6.0-3.fb7b7a553/&#34;&gt;our repository&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      </item> 
      <item>
        <title>Gaia Sky 3.6.0-2</title>
        <link>https://gaiasky.space/news/2024/gaiasky_3.6.0-2/</link>
        <pubDate>Thu, 14 Mar 2024 08:56:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid>https://gaiasky.space/news/2024/gaiasky_3.6.0-2/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;📢 Gaia Sky 3.6.0-2 available now!&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;features&#34;&gt;Features&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Annotate camera files with frame rate so that playback can adjust it automatically.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;bug-fixes&#34;&gt;Bug Fixes&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Camcorder play and record button inconsistent states.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;State handling in the camcorder.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;sleep(seconds)&lt;/code&gt; call also respects the camcorder FPS setting during recording.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Rename some API calls, deprecate old versions.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Add companion calls for camera orientation and position transitions.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Orbit coordinate not working when time is before the orbit start.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;You can get this release in &lt;a href=&#34;https://gaia.ari.uni-heidelberg.de/gaiasky/releases//3.6.0-2.4479175dc/&#34;&gt;our repository&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      </item> 
      <item>
        <title>Gaia Sky 3.6.0</title>
        <link>https://gaiasky.space/news/2024/gaiasky_3.6.0/</link>
        <pubDate>Tue, 12 Mar 2024 08:51:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid>https://gaiasky.space/news/2024/gaiasky_3.6.0/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;📢 Gaia Sky 3.6.0 available now!&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;features&#34;&gt;Features&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Add support for OptFlowCam (Piotrowski 2024) method to convert keyframes into camera path files. Gaia Sky calls the local python3 interpreter to process the keyframe files, so a local python3 installation (with numpy) needs to be in place for it to work.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Add support for B-splines, additionally to Catmull-Rom splines, as a method for interpolating positions between keyframes.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Reorganize keyframes window layout for better use of space.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Add different durations for the transitions in position and orientation in the API call.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Add smooth interpolation methods to &lt;code&gt;cameraTransition()&lt;/code&gt; calls. The new methods can use either a logistic sigmoid or a logit function. Smoothing factor is configurable via a parameter.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Add &amp;rsquo;textureAttribute&amp;rsquo; to particle sets, so that textures are selected with respect to the value of an attribute.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Use local dataset descriptors to construct catalog infos, when they are not explicitly set.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Enable local data information in the &amp;lsquo;+ info&amp;rsquo; window. This displays the local data on an object. In particle and star groups, the extra attributes are also offered.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Enable extra arguments of type string for star and particle sets.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Rename &amp;lsquo;star systems&amp;rsquo; group to &amp;rsquo;exoplanets &amp;amp; extrasolar systems&amp;rsquo;. Add icons to group title in dataset manager.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Add support for multiple key sets bound to actions in hotkey tooltip.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Keyframes and camera path file saving no longer overwrites existing files. Instead, it generates a new unique file name based on the given one.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Support comma- as well as whitespace-separated values for camera and keyframes files. Default to comma-separated values for writing.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Add API call to get the window coordinates of an object, in pixels.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Add API calls to do camera transitions only in position and orientation.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Add time transition API call and test script.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;bug-fixes&#34;&gt;Bug Fixes&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Check leap years in date dialog.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Prevent NaNs in some camera operations.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Clean up test scripts a bit.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;startRecordingCameraPath(String filename)&lt;/code&gt; does not use the filename correctly.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;build-system&#34;&gt;Build System&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Update dependency library versions.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;You can get this release in &lt;a href=&#34;https://gaia.ari.uni-heidelberg.de/gaiasky/releases//3.6.0.afdd9547d/&#34;&gt;our repository&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      </item> 
      <item>
        <title>Gaia Sky 3.5.9-2</title>
        <link>https://gaiasky.space/news/2024/gaiasky_3.5.9-2/</link>
        <pubDate>Thu, 22 Feb 2024 09:29:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid>https://gaiasky.space/news/2024/gaiasky_3.5.9-2/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;📢 Gaia Sky 3.5.9-2 available now!&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;bug-fixes&#34;&gt;Bug Fixes&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Individual object visibility API calls, and generic model alpha interpolation.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;build-system&#34;&gt;Build System&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Only add natives for the specific target platform in built packages.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;You can get this release in &lt;a href=&#34;https://gaia.ari.uni-heidelberg.de/gaiasky/releases//3.5.9-2.422e5e11c/&#34;&gt;our repository&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      </item> 
      <item>
        <title>Gaia Sky 3.5.9</title>
        <link>https://gaiasky.space/news/2024/gaiasky_3.5.9/</link>
        <pubDate>Mon, 19 Feb 2024 15:08:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid>https://gaiasky.space/news/2024/gaiasky_3.5.9/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;📢 Gaia Sky 3.5.9 available now!&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;features&#34;&gt;Features&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Add support for arbitrary affine transformations to datasets, and add controls to create and edit them in the datasets pane.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Separate filters from dataset preferences into their own button/window in datasets pane.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Improve layout of the filters window by moving the &amp;lsquo;add&amp;rsquo; button to the top and adding a scroll pane in the content.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Improve default window skin by adding some padding and a better sprite.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Rename dataset preferences to dataset visual settings. It now contains some sliders to modify the point size and the min/max solid angles. It does not contain filters or dataset information anymore, as those were extracted to their own dialogs.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Add affine transformations to all datasets (particle group, star group, variable star group, billboard group, orbit elements group). These transformations are applied in the shaders so that they can be updated on the fly. The billboard group object has been moved inside the generic catalog archetype; the Milky Way appears as a dataset now.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Add min/max particle solid angle size and number of labels to particle dataset load dialog.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Add support for additional texture(s) in raymarching shaders.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Do not force safe mode on Macs powered by apple silicon anymore.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;bug-fixes&#34;&gt;Bug Fixes&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Remove support for cloud SVT shadows, as this necessitates the cloud SVT and the diffuse SVT to be exactly the same (same depth, same available tiles, etc.), and this is not &lt;em&gt;usually&lt;/em&gt; the case.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Concurrency error in procedural generation progress bar update actions.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Present filter results in dataset manager in expanded panes.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Prevent the creation of multiple dataset preferences window for the same dataset.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Prevent NPE crash during the creation of the error dialog. Part of &lt;a href=&#34;https://codeberg.org/gaiasky/gaiasky/issues/765&#34;&gt;#765&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Prevent null pointer when updating star sets. Fixes &lt;a href=&#34;https://codeberg.org/gaiasky/gaiasky/issues/766&#34;&gt;#766&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Typo in French translation.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Appimage actually includes unpacked JRE distribution correctly.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;build-system&#34;&gt;Build System&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Add pgp signature to build process instead of checksums.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;You can get this release in &lt;a href=&#34;https://gaia.ari.uni-heidelberg.de/gaiasky/releases//3.5.9.51d1305ab/&#34;&gt;our repository&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      </item> 
      <item>
        <title>Gaia Sky 3.5.8-3</title>
        <link>https://gaiasky.space/news/2024/gaiasky_3.5.8-3/</link>
        <pubDate>Mon, 29 Jan 2024 18:40:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid>https://gaiasky.space/news/2024/gaiasky_3.5.8-3/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;📢 Gaia Sky 3.5.8-3 available now!&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;bug-fixes&#34;&gt;Bug Fixes&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Make sure a focus&amp;rsquo; star ancestor exists before trying to get its parenthood in the octree.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;You can get this release in &lt;a href=&#34;https://gaia.ari.uni-heidelberg.de/gaiasky/releases//3.5.8-3.600deaa6a/&#34;&gt;our repository&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      </item> 
      <item>
        <title>Gaia Sky 3.5.8-2</title>
        <link>https://gaiasky.space/news/2024/gaiasky_3.5.8-2/</link>
        <pubDate>Mon, 29 Jan 2024 10:04:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid>https://gaiasky.space/news/2024/gaiasky_3.5.8-2/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;📢 Gaia Sky 3.5.8-2 available now!&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 id=&#34;bug-fixes&#34;&gt;Bug Fixes&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Number of reported layers by OpenXR driver can be 0, otherwise app does not start. Fixes &lt;a href=&#34;https://codeberg.org/gaiasky/gaiasky/issues/763&#34;&gt;#763&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Visual settings reset operation implemented in one place only.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;You can get this release in &lt;a href=&#34;https://gaia.ari.uni-heidelberg.de/gaiasky/releases//3.5.8-2.4fd7a9705/&#34;&gt;our repository&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
