<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Access Issues on Gaia Sky</title>
    <link>https://gaiasky.space/tags/access-issues/</link>
    <description>Recent news in Access Issues on Gaia Sky</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
      <atom:link href="https://gaiasky.space/tags/access-issues/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" /> 
      <item>
        <title>🚧 Service update: university security measures continue 🚧</title>
        <link>https://gaiasky.space/news/2025/server-down-update/</link>
        <pubDate>Wed, 17 Dec 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid>https://gaiasky.space/news/2025/server-down-update/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s been a month now, and unfortunately, our main download server is still offline. We know this is quite frustrating for users, as it is for us too.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;For those just catching up: our server, which holds all the Gaia Sky installers, data packs, and docs, is hosted behind a Heidelberg University domain. About a month ago, the university&amp;rsquo;s IT center detected a widespread security incident and took major preventative action, which included taking our server (and many others) offline.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In short, this is a big university-wide security response, and we have no control over the timeline. We&amp;rsquo;re waiting just like everyone else.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;You can read the official updates from the university&amp;rsquo;s IT center (URZ) here:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.urz.uni-heidelberg.de/en/precautionary-measures&#34;&gt;Precautionary Measures by URZ&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.urz.uni-heidelberg.de/en/newsroom/news-it-security-incident-precautionary-measures&#34;&gt;URZ IT Security Incident&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;For Gaia Sky users, this means that:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;New users can&amp;rsquo;t download Gaia Sky from our official site right now.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;The project documentation is offline.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Data packs and other downloads are also inaccessible.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;However, the server works, but can only be reached via the university VPN.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;We&amp;rsquo;re really sorry about this. We&amp;rsquo;re a small team, and while this server situation is out of our hands, we&amp;rsquo;re looking into temporary options to get things rolling again. We&amp;rsquo;ll shout about it here as soon as we have a workaround.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Thanks for sticking with us. We&amp;rsquo;ll post another update the moment we hear anything concrete from the university or have an alternative to share.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;</description>
      </item> 
      <item>
        <title>🚧 Server inaccessible 🚧</title>
        <link>https://gaiasky.space/news/2025/server-down/</link>
        <pubDate>Sat, 22 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid>https://gaiasky.space/news/2025/server-down/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;We regret to inform our users that our server, hosting Gaia Sky packages, datasets, and documentation, is currently inaccessible from external networks. This is due to precautionary measures taken by the University Computing Center (URZ) at the University of Heidelberg.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;For more details on these measures, please refer to the official announcement from the URZ: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.urz.uni-heidelberg.de/en/precautionary-measures&#34;&gt;Precautionary Measures by URZ&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;We apologize for any inconvenience this may cause and will keep you updated as the situation evolves.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;</description>
      </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
