<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Access Issues on Gaia Sky</title>
    <link>https://gaiasky.space/tags/access-issues/</link>
    <description>Recent news in Access Issues on Gaia Sky</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
      <atom:link href="https://gaiasky.space/tags/access-issues/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" /> 
      <item>
        <title>Workaround to get Gaia Sky running</title>
        <link>https://gaiasky.space/news/2026/workaround-server/</link>
        <pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 06:01:55 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid>https://gaiasky.space/news/2026/workaround-server/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;In light of the current &lt;a href=&#34;https://gaiasky.space/news/server-down-update&#34;&gt;server downtime&lt;/a&gt;, we are creating this post describing how to get Gaia Sky up and running with the base data package.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Gaia Sky installer&lt;/strong&gt; &amp;ndash; first, you will need to download the installer for Gaia Sky version 3.7.0. Since our server is currently inaccessible, we have made this version available for download at the following link:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://codeberg.org/gaiasky/gaiasky/releases/tag/3.7.0&#34;&gt;Gaia Sky 3.7.0 Installer&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Please choose the appropriate installer for your operating system and follow the installation steps as usual.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Base data package&lt;/strong&gt; &amp;ndash; once Gaia Sky is installed, you need the base data package, which includes the Solar System, the Milky Way, and other essential objects. Download it (either in &lt;code&gt;zip&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;tar.gz&lt;/code&gt;) from the following link:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://codeberg.org/gaiasky/gsdata-basedata/releases/tag/v057&#34;&gt;Base Data Package v057&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;After downloading, extract the package to any location on your computer.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Move the dataset to Gaia Sky’s data directory&lt;/strong&gt; &amp;ndash; next, go into the extracted directory, and in it you should find the &lt;code&gt;default-data&lt;/code&gt; directory. Copy it into the Gaia Sky data directory. Where is the Gaia Sky data directory, you ask? Here&amp;rsquo;s its location depending on your operating system:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Windows&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;code&gt;C:\Users\%username%\.gaiasky\data&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Linux&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;code&gt;~/.local/share/gaiasky/data&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;macOS&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;code&gt;~/.gaiasky/data&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Ensure that the &lt;code&gt;default-data&lt;/code&gt; directory is placed directly within the &lt;code&gt;data&lt;/code&gt; folder. This will allow Gaia Sky to load the necessary resources correctly.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Compatibility with older datasets&lt;/strong&gt; &amp;ndash; for older versions of Gaia Sky, most of the datasets for stars, galaxies, nebulae, clusters, and other celestial objects should still work. While the current server downtime means new datasets cannot be fetched, you can continue using previously downloaded datasets from older versions without issues.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;final-notes&#34;&gt;Final notes&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This should give you a working Gaia Sky installation with the bare minimum. We appreciate your patience during this downtime and are working hard to restore full access to our services.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;</description>
      </item> 
      <item>
        <title>🚧 Service update: university security measures continue 🚧</title>
        <link>https://gaiasky.space/news/2025/server-down-update/</link>
        <pubDate>Wed, 17 Dec 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid>https://gaiasky.space/news/2025/server-down-update/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s been a month now, and unfortunately, our main download server is still offline. We know this is quite frustrating for users, as it is for us too.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;For those just catching up: our server, which holds all the Gaia Sky installers, data packs, and docs, is hosted behind a Heidelberg University domain. About a month ago, the university&amp;rsquo;s IT center detected a widespread security incident and took major preventative action, which included taking our server (and many others) offline.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In short, this is a big university-wide security response, and we have no control over the timeline. We&amp;rsquo;re waiting just like everyone else.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;You can read the official updates from the university&amp;rsquo;s IT center (URZ) here:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.urz.uni-heidelberg.de/en/precautionary-measures&#34;&gt;Precautionary Measures by URZ&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.urz.uni-heidelberg.de/en/newsroom/news-it-security-incident-precautionary-measures&#34;&gt;URZ IT Security Incident&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;For Gaia Sky users, this means that:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;New users can&amp;rsquo;t download Gaia Sky from our official site right now.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;The project documentation is offline.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Data packs and other downloads are also inaccessible.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;However, the server works, but can only be reached via the university VPN.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;We&amp;rsquo;re really sorry about this. We&amp;rsquo;re a small team, and while this server situation is out of our hands, we&amp;rsquo;re looking into temporary options to get things rolling again. We&amp;rsquo;ll shout about it here as soon as we have a workaround.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Thanks for sticking with us. We&amp;rsquo;ll post another update the moment we hear anything concrete from the university or have an alternative to share.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;</description>
      </item> 
      <item>
        <title>🚧 Server inaccessible 🚧</title>
        <link>https://gaiasky.space/news/2025/server-down/</link>
        <pubDate>Sat, 22 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid>https://gaiasky.space/news/2025/server-down/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;We regret to inform our users that our server, hosting Gaia Sky packages, datasets, and documentation, is currently inaccessible from external networks. This is due to precautionary measures taken by the University Computing Center (URZ) at the University of Heidelberg.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;For more details on these measures, please refer to the official announcement from the URZ: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.urz.uni-heidelberg.de/en/precautionary-measures&#34;&gt;Precautionary Measures by URZ&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;We apologize for any inconvenience this may cause and will keep you updated as the situation evolves.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;</description>
      </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
