<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Website on Gaia Sky</title>
    <link>https://gaiasky.space/categories/website/</link>
    <description>Recent news in Website on Gaia Sky</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
      <atom:link href="https://gaiasky.space/categories/website/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" /> 
      <item>
        <title>Gaia Sky server back online!</title>
        <link>https://gaiasky.space/news/2026/server-available/</link>
        <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2026 11:31:55 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid>https://gaiasky.space/news/2026/server-available/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;After several months of &lt;a href=&#34;https://gaiasky.space/news/2025/server-down-update&#34;&gt;downtime&lt;/a&gt;, we are excited and relieved to announce that the &lt;strong&gt;Gaia Sky server is officially back online&lt;/strong&gt; and accessible to the public!&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;figure class=&#34;fig-center fig-post&#34;&gt;&lt;picture&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://gaiasky.space/img/2026/gaia-connect.svg&#34; width=&#34;64px&#34; style=&#34;width:64px;&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34;decoding=&#34;async&#34; /&gt;&#xA;    &lt;/picture&gt;&#xA;&lt;/figure&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Thanks to our colleagues of the IT department in our institute, we could open up our server so that Gaia Sky users can again download the application and the data packages without restrictions.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;We know it has been a long wait, and we appreciate the patience the community has shown during this university-wide incident.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Everything you need to get back to exploring the cosmos is ready for download:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://gaiasky.space/downloads&#34;&gt;Release Packages&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/strong&gt; You can once again download the latest installers for Linux, Windows, and macOS.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://gaiasky.space/resources/datasets&#34;&gt;Datasets&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/strong&gt; The full catalog of datasets, from the base star catalogs to the high-resolution texture packs, is again reachable via the internal dataset manager and as manual downloads.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://gaiasky.space/docs&#34;&gt;Documentation&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/strong&gt; The Gaia Sky documentation pages are also open now.&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;</description>
      </item> 
      <item>
        <title>Workaround to get Gaia Sky running</title>
        <link>https://gaiasky.space/news/2026/workaround-server/</link>
        <pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 06:01:55 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid>https://gaiasky.space/news/2026/workaround-server/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;In light of the current &lt;a href=&#34;https://gaiasky.space/news/server-down-update&#34;&gt;server downtime&lt;/a&gt;, we are creating this post describing how to get Gaia Sky up and running with the base data package.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Gaia Sky installer&lt;/strong&gt; &amp;ndash; first, you will need to download the installer for Gaia Sky version 3.7.0. Since our server is currently inaccessible, we have made this version available for download at the following link:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://codeberg.org/gaiasky/gaiasky/releases/tag/3.7.0&#34;&gt;Gaia Sky 3.7.0 Installer&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Please choose the appropriate installer for your operating system and follow the installation steps as usual.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Base data package&lt;/strong&gt; &amp;ndash; once Gaia Sky is installed, you need the base data package, which includes the Solar System, the Milky Way, and other essential objects. Download it (either in &lt;code&gt;zip&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;tar.gz&lt;/code&gt;) from the following link:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://codeberg.org/gaiasky/gsdata-basedata/releases/tag/v057&#34;&gt;Base Data Package v057&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;After downloading, extract the package to any location on your computer.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Move the dataset to Gaia Sky’s data directory&lt;/strong&gt; &amp;ndash; next, go into the extracted directory, and in it you should find the &lt;code&gt;default-data&lt;/code&gt; directory. Copy it into the Gaia Sky data directory. Where is the Gaia Sky data directory, you ask? Here&amp;rsquo;s its location depending on your operating system:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Windows&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;code&gt;C:\Users\%username%\.gaiasky\data&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Linux&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;code&gt;~/.local/share/gaiasky/data&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;macOS&lt;/strong&gt;: &lt;code&gt;~/.gaiasky/data&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Ensure that the &lt;code&gt;default-data&lt;/code&gt; directory is placed directly within the &lt;code&gt;data&lt;/code&gt; folder. This will allow Gaia Sky to load the necessary resources correctly.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Compatibility with older datasets&lt;/strong&gt; &amp;ndash; for older versions of Gaia Sky, most of the datasets for stars, galaxies, nebulae, clusters, and other celestial objects should still work. While the current server downtime means new datasets cannot be fetched, you can continue using previously downloaded datasets from older versions without issues.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 id=&#34;final-notes&#34;&gt;Final notes&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This should give you a working Gaia Sky installation with the bare minimum. We appreciate your patience during this downtime and are working hard to restore full access to our services.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;</description>
      </item> 
      <item>
        <title>New homepage</title>
        <link>https://gaiasky.space/news/2025/new-site/</link>
        <pubDate>Fri, 31 Jan 2025 09:41:55 +0000</pubDate>
        <guid>https://gaiasky.space/news/2025/new-site/</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Today we publish the new Gaia Sky web site. If you are reading this, you obviously know it. I&amp;rsquo;ve been working on this for a while, and, even though it is not yet finished, I think it is now ready to be deployed. Until now, we have used the website of &lt;a href=&#34;https://zah.ari.uni-heidelberg.de&#34;&gt;our institute&lt;/a&gt;, which uses the Typo3 CMS, as our home page. In a few days, I&amp;rsquo;ll make it point to this new site.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;It is easier to add content to, and easier to maintain. I also happen to think it looks better. I hope you enjoy it.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The canonical URL, for now, is this:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://gaiasky.space&#34;&gt;https://gaiasky.space&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;</description>
      </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
